Good morning.
Today's דף Daf is
דף קכד, Daf Kof Kaf Dalet, 124, 44th day of the עומר,
Omer, so we're like about a week before שבועות, Shavuos, and we
pick up at the bottom of קכג עמוד ב, Kof Kaf Gimmel
Amud Bais, and we are in the middle of a discussion of
whether a בכור Bechor gets double in the property, in the increase
of value of the property after the father dies. Now the general
rule is that he should not because it's a principle of that
a בכור Bechor does not get בראוי Brauy in stuff that is
sitting to come to the father כבמוחזק Kebemuchzak in the way that
he gets with stuff that's already in the father's possession. Nevertheless, the
ברייתא Baraita basically said that if the sort of property increases in
value that he does get double. Now one way and it distinguished
between whether it increased by value naturally or did the heirs build
houses on it and therefore because of their investment it increased in
value and that would determine whether he gets double or not. So
we are going to see that that is going to be a
principle of רבי Rebbi that is not agreed upon by others, it's
going to be a heavily debated principle. Others say no, I'm sorry,
the father has to be in full possession of it, but רבי
Rebbi is going to say that property that will, the natural increase
or increase of a value of a property that is not coming
through any investment of the heirs and happens as it were by
itself and you have to define what by itself means, it's considered
as if it were already in the father's possession and therefore the
בכור Bechor gets double. Okay, now so let's take a look at
that. So we pick up with imagine like let's say you have
a cow who's, you know, it's a baby and by the time
it grows up, it grows up, I mean you divide, is he
going to say no, you only get the value before it grows
up, exactly, exactly, exactly. Now one of the ways to ask this
question is to say it's not really that the בכור Bechor gets
double in the increased value, it's that once the בכור Bechor holds
double in the principle, then automatically he will get double in the
increased value. If we all have, if they inherit a bank account
from the father and there's a million dollars in the bank account
and the בכור Bechor gets, you know, whatever it is, six hundred
and sixty thousand and the other guy gets three hundred and thirty
thousand, okay, and then the bank account earns interest, well the בכור
Bechor gets his interest on his two-thirds and the other guy gets
interest on his one-third. So it's not that he's getting double in
like, you know, the פי שנים Pishnayim of something that came from
the father, he already has a double stake in it and he's
getting naturally the increased value. But תוספות Tosafot says that actually no,
that would only work once they divided the property. If they have
not yet divided the property and they have not yet each claimed
their stake, then you do not view it as if he already
has two-thirds of the principle and it's his principle that's increasing, you
view it as if the estate now has gained more value and
therefore we have to ask is the בכור Bechor entitled to a
double not because he owns double of the principle but the estate
increased in value and is he entitled to double of the stuff
that came naturally. Okay, so as Michael points out, that'll sometimes
happen automatically, an animal grows up, you know, and we haven't gotten
around to dividing the estate, so that's probably part of רבי's Rebbi
position, stuff that's natural growth is not considered like ראוי, Rauy, that's
considered like it would have happened by itself, it did happen by
itself, you know, and therefore it's like it was already under the
father's possession. Let me just lead to distinction, another way to say
is if they count money into the estate and then they divide
it, yes, so say the interest was one hundred percent, right, so
sixty-six percent of the interest is going to go, sixty percent is
going to go to the first, right, thirty to the, so what's
the difference between that and saying that he, no, no, no, so
that's what I said, תוספות, Tosafot, you only get, the idea that
you own an extra portion in the principle and would naturally get
the increase in the principle not because of just because now you
own it, is only once they divide the estate. Before they divide
the estate you don't look at it that way yet, you just
look at it as that this is the property of the estate.
So even though the בכור Bechor is going to take two-thirds out
of the estate, he hasn't taken it yet. So the increased value
in the estate is not yet an increase in the בכור's Bechor
value, it's an increase in the value of the estate. But he'll
still get the two-thirds later. No, he won't, if you don't increase
the estate, it's two-thirds of that. Okay, here's the estate, okay, it's
worth a million dollars, alright, so if they basically divide it, alright,
and the, this would be the בכור, Bechor, these will be here
the others, I guess we'll do it this way because then he'll
get half, okay, okay, if they've divided it, alright, and he gets
his five hundred thousand and they each get their two hundred and
fifty, okay, and then it earns money, then everybody's earning money on
their principle, okay, you don't need any הלכה Halacha about does a
בכור. Bechor. He's already taken his property and therefore he gets the
increase of value, whether it's physical property, whether he moved it into
his own bank account, whatever he did. But if he hasn't moved
it into his own bank account and they haven't divided it up,
and this all still is under the bank account
of John's estate, we haven't divided it into different bank accounts, okay,
and now it increased in value and now there's an extra 10,000
here, okay, his two-thirds didn't grow by 10,000, he doesn't have, or
his half, he doesn't have his half yet. The estate now had
a million dollars from before the guy died, plus 10,000 dollars that
it increased in value after the guy died. Then the בכור bechor
comes on, he says, "I'd like to collect my half of the
estate." So we say, "Okay, you get your half of what it
was when your father died because that's,
because that's the הלכה halacha that you get double what your father
owned when he died. This amount that increased the value of the
estate, that was an increase in value after your father died. You
guys are going to divide it equally." Okay, so, oh, I see,
so you each get a third of that. All right, so the
thing would be the, oh, okay, fine. All right, so if you
already divide it, then your property has increased in value, but if
not it's the estate, you get half, you get double portion in
what the father had. But what רבי Rebbe says is no, even
if you haven't divided it yet, the increase in value that happens
naturally is like it happened already under the, under the before the
father died, and it's like it was already in the possession of
the father, and the בכור bechor gets a double stake in that
increase of value as well. Okay, so let's take a look at
that in the גמרא. Gemara. גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
four lines, five lines from the bottom on קכג עמוד ב. kuf
chaf gimmel amud bet.
הניח להם אביהם פרה מושכרת ומושכרת ביד אחרים, Hiniach lahem avihem parah
mushkeret umuskeret beyad acheirim, if their father left them a cow that
was rented out to others or מושכרת mushkeret is that others are
like doing business with it and they're splitting the profits, okay, או
שהייתה רועה באפר o shehayeta roah ba'eifer or if it was just
grazing out in the like wilderness, okay, meaning that they weren't like
feeding it, buying food for it, וילדה veyaleda and it gave birth,
בכור נוטל פי שנים bechor notel pi shenayim the בכור bechor gets
double. So first גמרא Gemara says, wait minute, השתא מושכרת ומושכרת דאבירו
רשותא דמרא דיקאי קיימא, hashta mushkeret umuskeret de'aviru reshuta demara dikai kaima,
if you're telling me that even when it's rented out where it's
like not physically under the control—I mean they own it, but it's
not physically under the control of the estate—and nevertheless it's considered like
the increase in value, because remember, conceptually we have to say it's
like that natural increase in value was already existed and already under
the control of the father. So it's harder to say that if
the principal is out of the father's direct control. I mean he's
renting it, right, but to say it's like he already had the
value increase of the
cow before he died with this cow that's rented out to other
people, not even on his property, that's already if we're going to
say there it's like the father already had that increase in value,
so אמרת שקיל amarta shakil you say that he gets a double
stake, it's like the father already had that, so רועה באפר roah
ba'eifer just grazing out in the field מיבעיא miba'ya should there be
any question? Of course that's directly under the father's control, it's a
natural increase in value, of course that should be considered like the
father already had that. No, the גמרא Gemara says הכא קא משמע
לן hacha kamashma lan here's what it's teaching you. דמושכרת ומושכרת דומיא
דרועה באפר Demushkeret umuskeret dumiya deroah ba'eifer the case of rented out
is similar to the case of grazing. מה רועה באפר שבחא דממילא
קא אתי ולא קא חסי ביה מזוני Ma roah ba'eifer shivcha demimeila
ka ati velo kachasi beimezona the emphasis is רועה באפר roah ba'eifer
grazing out literally in the dust, but meaning that he's just grazing
in the wild and it does not require any investment from the
heirs. It happens totally by itself. So the same way that case,
it happened totally by itself and they don't have to make any
investment of time or money or whatever and that's why it's like
it happened automatically and it was already under the father's control, so
אף מושכרת ומושכרת af mushkeret umuskeret so similarly the case where it's
rented out, שבחא דממילא shivcha demimeila they would only get double if
the, if the, if it happened by itself, if they didn't have
to say, if I was renting out my cow to David there
and the agreement was was that I would pay for the food
bills and David would pay me though the rental fees, then that
wouldn't apply because the benefit is only accruing to me because of
a investment that I am making. Okay, and therefore it's not like
it's seen as automatic and therefore it's not like it's seen like
the father already had it under his control. If David were to
feed it, then you would get it. Right, if David were to
feed it I would, of course the point is David still had
to make an investment, so the point is, right, that's all very
nice for David, but what do I care? Like that's a black
box, you know what I'm saying, like I don't have to invest
anything, I just get total automatic benefit. It's all very nice that
like or it's מושכרת mushkeret you have to go around and do
business with it, so that is an important conceptual difference because you
could say things that happen just naturally, a tree grows, that's like
it already happened. But something that requires like, you know, effort to
make it happen, David has to hustle a bit if he wants
to make a profit with his cow, so maybe that's not automatic.
But the point is though, from my perspective, David might have to
hustle. It wouldn't necessarily have definitely accrued to the father if David
didn't do his work. But the fact is is that at least
since the father and now the heirs don't have to make an
investment and don't then it's like it just happened automatically. And therefore
it's like the father already have it. So אף מוחכרת ומושכרת שבחא
דממילא קאתי ולא חסידי מזוני Af muchkeret u’mushkeret shevacha dimimeila ka'asi v'lo
chasidai mezoni that they are not actually having to pay for the
food. And you look at the Rashbam. The Rashbam says exactly what
we just said.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina, if you look at the second
narrow line of the Rashbam. סלקא דעתך אמינא כל מוחכרת ומושכרת לאו
שבחא דממילא הוא. salka da'atach amina kol muchkeret u’mushkeret lav shevacha dimimeila
hu. That's not automatic. The other guy's got to go ahead and
feed it and he's got to hustle if it's about making a
profit with it. Okay. אלא על ידי בני אדם שחורשין בה ועובדים
בה לאו שבחא דבכור פי שנים. ella al yedei bnei adam shechorshin
bah v'ovdim bah lav shevacha d'bechor pi shnayim. קא משמע לן, ka
mashma lan, it teaches us that since the יתומים עצמם yetomim atzmam
ain't חורשין בהן chorshin bahen and they don't toil in them, but
others, שבחא דממילא חשבינן ליה היכא דאין מעלין למזונות. shevacha dimimeila chashvinan
lei heicha d'ein ma'alin limzonot. So from their perspective they don't have
to invest any time or money or effort, so it's automatic. And
that's enough to make it considered as if the father was already
under control and under the control of the father and the בכור
bechor gets double, yes. Now things can get a little tricky, like
let's say the tree grows, but you know, then you can say,
alright, but you know, I helped it along because I like fertilized
it, I pruned it. Right, right. And you say, alright, well it
rained, okay but I watered it the other days.
So that's an interesting question like, a, how much effort is effort?
Like let's say you did a minimal stuff, if it would have
grown anyway, but like you still, you know, you still invested a
minimal amount of effort, right? Or what if you say like I
watered it and then it rained, so now we find out retroactively
I wouldn't have had to have watered it. So right, I don't
know exactly how to measure those things. That's a very good question.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מני, mani, now
who is this ברייתא Baraita going like that says that when it
happens automatically the בכור bechor gets double? רבי היא, Rabbi hi, it's
רבי. Rabbi. דתניא: dtanya: אין בכור נוטל פי שנים בשבח ששבחו נכסים
לאחר מיתת אביהם. ein bechor notel pi shnayim beshevach sheshavchu nechasim l'achar
mitat avihem. The בכור bechor does not get double by the increase
of value that happened after the father died. רבי אומר, Rabbi omer,
רבי Rabbi says, אומר אני, omer ani, but I say, שהבכור נוטל
פי שנים בשבח ששבחו נכסים לאחר מיתת אביהם, shehabechor notel pi shnayim
beshevach sheshavchu nechasim l'achar mitat avihem, that he does get double. אבל,
aval, but here's the difference: לא בשבח ששבחו יתומים לאחר מיתת אביהם.
lo beshevach sheshivchu yetomim l'achar mitat avihem. When it happens by itself,
the property increases in value, but not an increase that happens due
to the fact that the heirs caused it to increase in value,
right? So not something that happens automatically, not that happens through effort
and investment. And as Michael said, you know, obviously there's a big
question how you'd draw the line.
Okay, so now we're going to give some cases. ירשו שטר חוב,
yarshu shtar chov, בכור נוטל פי שנים. bechor notel pi shnayim. So
if they inherited
a debt, meaning the, you know, what is it, accounts receivable, right?
Right, right. Somebody owed them money, okay, so the בכור bechor gets
double. Now the question that the גמרא's Gemara going to ask is,
who is that according to? Is that according to רבי Rabbi and
collecting a debt is considered to be
שבחא דממילא shevacha dimimeila because, you know, the guy has to pay
up what he owes you, etc.? But it's not considered normal מוחזק?
muchzak? Or maybe it's even according to the רבנן? Rabbanan? Since people
owe money to the father, it's in his accounts receivable, it was
money that he lent out, that money that's coming back, so maybe
it's considered to be like already under the control of the father,
right? I mean, you could imagine that, right? Guy has a big
company or whatever, you know, he shipped out all this stuff, he's
waiting for the payments to come in. Is the payments ראוי ra'uy
or is it מוחזק? muchzak? Okay. And by the way, when we
say, does this mean I borrowed a hundred dollars from you...
Wait, don't make me... I'm going to be the person who died
in this scenario. You borrowed a hundred dollars from ראובן. Reuven. Okay,
right, exactly. לבן עין. Lavan Ayin. Okay, yeah, exactly.
I'm sorry. That's alright, part
of it. Yeah, so I borrowed a hundred dollars from ראובן, Reuven,
ראובן Reuven died, I now have to pay two hundred dollars to...
No, no, no. You pay your hundred dollars and then the question
is how do the heirs divide it? Does the בכור bechor get
double? But the question is, even putting רבי Rabbi aside, it's, you
know, when the property, the cow gives birth, the property goes up
in value, you know, somebody makes profit, somebody pays a rental fee
on an apartment that they're renting. If all of that happens afterwards,
you understand logically you would say that's ראוי. ra'uy. And then רבי
Rabbi has to say, ah, but if it happened automatically it's like
it's מוחזק. muchzak. But money that is coming to the father because
he lent it out or because he sold something and is now
is waiting for payment, my intuition would be to call that מוחזק.
muchzak. Like it's true he might not get it, but he deserves
it, he's already given what... you know, there's some... anyway, I'm more
של מוציא מחברו. shel motzi mechavero. Right. Yeah, gloria. In US law,
that would be considered part of the estate because the obligation to
get the payment, I mean if it's—aha. So like when you pay
estate taxes, you have to pay it based on accounts receivable as
well? Oh, interesting. Now even though it's true that like for let's
say companies, they normally would write—write off 10% of their accounts receivable
or something like that. They don't always get paid, right? So you
still figure out the 100% or you do it based on some
formula? What they record it on the books. Ah, I see, I
see. I see. So once the accounts get paid, then retroactively we
know that was what the estate had and that's—that's what you pay
estate taxes based on. Something like—is that what you're saying? Something like
that.
No? Not quite. Well, I guess a business and a person are
different. Okay, but the basic point is that the accounts receivable or
debts owed are pretty much considered part of the estate, not—not an
increase in value that occurred later. Right. That makes total sense, yeah.
Does any of this have to do with whether שטר חוב העומד
לגבות כגבוי דמי? shtar chov ha'omed ligbot k'gavuy dami? Oh, something like
that. Yeah, and we'll talk about—I mean the גמרא Gemara doesn't directly
address that, but it definitely intersects with that. Okay, so that's a
line and we're going to try to figure out if that line
is only according to רבי Rebbi or even according to the רבנן.
Rabbanan. And at some point it makes a difference if it's like
a 50-year loan or something, right? Right, and—I'm sorry, what? Well, he
won't get the value until it's actually paid though, right? Right, right.
Okay, even 50 years later. Yeah. Okay. שטר חוב ובכורתו פי שנים.
shtar chov u-v'chornato pi shenayim. יצא עליהם
שטר חוב. yatza aleihem shtar chov. Now let's say the estate owes
money, okay? Somebody comes and says, yeah, your father owes me $10,000.
So בכור נותן פי שנים. bechor noten pi shenayim. So that person
has a lien
on—he only has a lien on the קרקע, karka, okay? So first
of all, if they inherited a million dollars cash and the guy
comes with a $10,000
debt, the sons don't have to pay because that lien—it's like they—it's
considered like they bought that money off—they bought—they took that money off
their father, right? If someone owes someone money and then he transfers
all of his property to someone else, the creditor can only collect
the stuff that has a lien, not the chattel, like not the
cash. So the father dies, they get this cash, the cash doesn't
have any liens on it, so they don't have to pay out
any debts to the estate, right? Now the גאונים Geonim later changed
that. When things moved to a commercial society, the גאונים Geonim changed
that, because you could imagine, right? Someone's a smart businessman and he
knows he's going to die soon, what he just does is he
borrows a lot of money and he transfers all of his assets
to cash, and then he's able to bequeath to his heirs everything
and the debts don't have to get paid up. Okay anyway but
that's the principle.
Anyway that's the rule, but it got changed in the time of
the גאונים. Geonim. But anyway, but the guy—the creditor has a lien
on the real estate, okay? And so the בכור bechor now gets
an extra portion of the real estate, he gets two-thirds and the
other brother gets a third, then this guy has to get two-thirds
of his payment from the בכור bechor and one-third from the
brother, because his liens are equally distributed. Now of course the interesting
question is, let's say he just goes to one of them. He
just goes to the brother or just goes to the בכור. bechor.
Do you then redistribute the estate because now conceptually you look at
it as like, oh in hindsight it's like the estate actually had
less value? Right? So he doesn't have to go and say I'm
taking two-thirds from that portion over there and one-third from that—right, that's
not fair to the creditor. He collects from wherever he finds it,
and then they might have to redistribute it. But the reality is
is that an extra portion comes from the בכור bechor because either
because you imagine that the liens are equally distributed like so therefore
he has extra liens on the בכור bechor estate, or you view
it as in hindsight the estate was smaller, and therefore the distribution
is—so if he got an extra portion, now that we're shrinking it,
proportionally he loses an extra proportional amount as well. We actually say
that like if they distributed it again and then they gotta—yeah, that
was the גמרא—we Gemara had that discussion in the גמרא Gemara about
how you do that. Yeah. Okay, so יצא עליהם שטר חוב yatza
aleihem shtar chov if there's a debt against them, בכור נותן פי
שנים. bechor noten pi shenayim. So he has to actually give an
extra portion to pay off that debt. Okay, ואם אמר ve-im amar
now if the בכור bechor says איני נותן ואיני נוטל. eini noten
ve-eini notel. You know what, it's like I waive my right to
the double portion. I'm not going to get my extra portion and
I'm not going to give—I'm not going to have my extra portion
go to paying this creditor, so רשאי. rashai. He is permitted. Now—but—meaning
he's done the accounting and he realizes he'd be out on a
hole. He could do it at any—well he could do it before.
No, after doing the accounting. But let's talk about this. First of
all, this is an interesting חידוש, chiddush, and it's only true about
the extra portion and it's not true about the prime portion. I
mentioned to you earlier that a case about a guy that this
community forced him because he had a whole fight with his mother,
the community basically they're like I'm going to write you out of
my will, the community basically forced this guy to write himself out
of his mother's will to basically say I'm waiving my rights to
my mother's estate. state, and then his mother died and then he
said, no, I still want it. Okay, so and they basically said
no, he, even though in principle he's still entitled, but because of
the community sort of edict he can't take it. But the point
is, a person cannot, whether they do it before their, their what's
the point,
what's the name of the guy who bequeaths property? Not benefactor, whatever.
Anyway, before, what? There's a word for it. Anyway, before their parent
dies, let's just say, you know, or after, a person cannot say
I am waiving my rights to the estate. No, it happens automatically.
You can write a million times and do a million קניינים, kinyanim,
you are still going to get your portion in the estate. After
you get it, you can give it to somebody else, but you
cannot prevent yourself from getting it. As opposed to the extra חלק
chelek of the בכור. bechor. Because there it says לתת לו פי
שנים. lateit lo pishnayim. So it's not just, it's not a ירושה,
yerusha, it's seen in some ways as a מתנה, matana, as a
gift. So if you try to gift me something, and I'm saying,
right like you know, you know, Dave there tries to gift me
a Ferrari to Michael and he gives Michael the key and we
say, you know, you know what is it, זכין לאדם שלא בפניו.
zakhin leadam shelo befanav. And Michael's going to be קונה koneh the
car there for me, he's going to drive it onto my property,
whatever קניין kinyan he's going to do and I'm yelling, no, no,
I don't want it, I don't want it! So I don't get
it. I can't make me get something against my will. So if
the בכור bechor says I waive my פי שנים, pishnayim, he doesn't
get it. Okay, even just, even just verbally waiving it before, you
know, before the guy, before the father died. If he does it
after the father dies, that's an interesting question at what stage can
he do it? Okay, but he can do it even verbally and
so on. So that's an interesting point. That he can waive his
double portion. Now the question is, what would motivate him to do
so? Okay, so now, okay, but he's not going to have to
give an extra portion that exceeds what he received. Okay, if, if
the father has a million dollars in debt and the estate is
worth $100,000,
the estate pays off $100,000 and then it's done. The בכור bechor
doesn't have to pay an extra portion from his own personal property.
Okay, so what is going to motivate you? You'll never going to
lose by taking it and giving it. So one thing that would
motivate you is if you're going to lose it all, if, if
the, if the debt exceeds the value, okay, or equal or exceed
the value, like it's like why do you bother, why do you
need the effort? Why am I going to bother to go ahead
and take possession of this property if I know he's going to
שלעפ shlep me to court and I'm going to have to give
it up anyway? Okay, so one thing is it's just not worth
the bother. Of course, the point is, you're going to be taken
to court regardless because he's going to take from you and from
all the brothers and he's going to take it all. So what
difference does it make if he winds up taking two-thirds from you
and a third from the brother or he takes half and half
from both of you, he's going to שלעפ shlep all you guys
to court anyway. So, so תוספות Tosafot says like you could imagine
a scenario, let's say, and like the, the brothers are minors. So
he can't take the brothers to court. So by the בכור bechor
waiving his double portion, what he really does is he protects that
amount. So he's going to take, you know, me to court cause
I'm an adult and he's going to get part of his payment
from me, but the rest of the estate he can't collect yet
cause my, cause my siblings are all minors. So by waiving my
double portion, I protect that amount from immediately being seized by this
guy. It's rolling it back in to the general into the general
estate for the minor siblings. Now, eventually, eventually he'll be able to
collect it, but maybe, but you know, like it's always better to
push these things off til later, you know? Like you know the
story, like maybe the cow will die, maybe the king will die,
maybe I'll teach the horse to sing. So anyway, so all right,
so anyway but he's got some motivation that he wants to avoid
dealing with, you know, he's going to lose it anyway, so he's
just going to waive his right. So he's allowed to do that.
All right, by the way רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam has a, another
interesting read of this line. He says this case of the בכור
bechor waiving his double portion is not a scenario where there's a,
there's a debt against the estate. It's a scenario where somebody has
a debt against the בכור. bechor. I personally owe Michael a $100,000.
I'm about to receive a double portion, okay, and it's, I know
it's going to go straight to Michael, okay, my, my primary inheritance
and my double portion to pay it off. So what I say
is, you know what, forget it, I don't want the double portion.
I'd rather my brothers get it, okay, rather than Michael. Now that
means that Michael's not going to get his debt paid, okay? He
can, I still owe it to you, but I might never get
enough money to pay it. And when am I ever going to
get a million dollars? The only way I got it was through
that inheritance. Okay, right? So, so,
so that allows my brothers, I mean, I'm still going to get
now my, whatever, we're going to divide it equally, but a lot
of it is now going to be taken by my brothers and
protected. It's an early asset protection program. Right, right. Now I still,
I still owe the money to Michael, but because I never received
that double portion, he might never get it. Okay, so that's the
way רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam reads that. Okay, so that's where we.
What? Now Michael's leaving, he's not getting his money, he's out of
here. Okay, so we're moving on. Okay, so now מאי טעמא דרבנן?
mai ta'ama de-rabbanan? Now, now
we go
what is the reason of the rabbis that say that the בכור
bechor does not get double in the increase that happened naturally? אמר
קרא amar kra because the verse says, לתת לו פי שנים, latet
lo pi shnayim, מתנה קרי רחמנא. mattana karei Rachmana.
It's called a gift. מה מתנה עד דמטי לידיה, mah mattana ad
demati lideih, the same way you can't give a gift until you
have possession of it, אף חלק בכורה עד דמטי לידיה, af chelek
bechorah ad demati lideih, the father cannot give the double portion until
he gets possession of it. So anything that came after the father's
death, it's not a double portion. ורבי אומר, ve-Rabbi omer, Rabbi says,
אמר קרא, amar kra, פי שנים, pi shnayim,
double. מה מקיש חלק בכורה לחלק פשוט, mah makkish chelek bechorah le-chelek
pashut, the extra portion is equated to the normal. מה חלק פשוט
אף על גב דלא מטא לידיה, mah chelek pashut af al gav
de-lo mata lideih, the same way the normal portion the heirs get
the increase even though it happened naturally, even though the father didn't
realize it, it was only realized after he died, but the heirs
get the increase, אף חלק בכורה אף על גב דלא מטא לידיה,
af chelek bechorah af al gav de-lo mata lideih, so the double
portion even though the father did not realize the increase, the בכור
bechor gets it. Of course, that's a bad answer because that sounds
like the principle of ראוי. ra'ui. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, רבנן נמי הכתיב פי שנים, Rabbanan nami haktiv pi shnayim, doesn't
the rabbi say it says double, which means it's like the principle
of- it's like the normal portion? No. ההוא למסמך ליה אחד מצרא.
hahu lemismach leih achad metzra. That means the fact that it's compared
to the basic portion means you don't give the בכור bechor one
portion in the north and one in the south and the other
brothers get in the middle. You give the בכור bechor his two
portions together, so it's one bigger plot of land. Okay, you treat
it as one big portion, not as two separate portions. Got that?
So that's why, right? That's why okay. So there's a מחלוקת machloket
here in the- in other words- Yeah, the רבנן Rabbanan say that
the בכור bechor does not get double for what increases naturally. He
only gets double for exactly what was in the father's possession. But
is Rabbi saying that he cannot
give up that second portion because it's not like a מתנה? mattana?
No, no, that part he agrees to. He just doesn't agree to
equating it to a מתנה mattana to the fact that it has
to be fully owned by the father before in order to get
double. But he says מה מקיש חלק בכורה לחלק פשוט. mah makkish
chelek bechorah le-chelek pashut. Right? Yeah. It's like you can't give up
the חלק פשוט? chelek pashut? No, but we're not applying it to
that. We're only applying- no, no, we're not- you're going ahead in
the ברייתא. braita. Right now we're just applying it to the principle
about whether he gets the natural increase of the property. Okay. Yes.
So if the בכור bechor is going to be responsible and all
the children are going to be responsible for debts that the father
owed, right? But so then why isn't the firstborn also able
to receive the money that's going to come into the estate? Why
isn't- you know what I'm saying? Shouldn't it be an equal balance
on both sides of the equation?
I'm sorry, one more time? It's different- different from the cow that
grew, but say, you know, if the estate owes money and if
the estate is owed money, why shouldn't the בכור bechor get that
money even though it's not yet in the estate if he's going
to have to- Okay, I understand. Let's get to the case of
when it's owed money and then I'll go back and hopefully answer
your question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so
don't the rabbis say that the בכור's bechor extra portion is like
the basic amount? So it says yes, but that's just to say
that it's one larger portion and he gets the two portions together,
not in separate places. ורבי נמי הכתיב לתת לו, ve-Rabbi nami haktiv
latet lo, to give it to him. Okay, and here you go
Rabbi Dov answering your question, it's like a מתנה. mattana. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, ההוא, hahu, the reason it's compared to מתנה
mattana is to tell you שאם אמר איני נוטל ואיני נותן, she-im
amar eini notel ve-eini noten, I'd rather not take it and not
give it, רשאי. rashai. Meaning yes, everybody agrees that it's like a
מתנה mattana to say like I said before that he can waive
it and and say I refuse to accept the extra portion. But
the question is, but Rabbi says I'm not going to make the
comparison full and I'm not going to say that he only will
get double in what the father fully possessed. It is enough like
the other portions of the estate that he will continue to get
double even in natural increase in property. Okay? So everybody agrees that
he gets the two portions together, everybody agrees that he can waive
the extra portion that he gets. The debate is does he get
the natural increase in property? Rabbis say no, it has to be
like a מתנה, mattana, it has to have been
fully possessed by the father. And Rabbi says yes, it's like the
same way anybody's portion, they get the increase in value, the בכור
bechor also gets the increase the natural increase in value. Okay? And
now the גמרא Gemara continues. So אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa,
now says Rav Pappa, Rav Pappa tries to narrow their debate even
further. דיקלא ואלים, dikla ve-alim, if it was a palm tree that
got thicker, ארעא ואסיק שירטון, ara ve-assik shirton, or if it's like
a piece of land that now got like, I don't know, enriched,
but it's like the thing is seen. So אמר רב פפא, Amar
Rav Pappa, now says רב פפא. Rav Pappa. רב פפא Rav Pappa
tries to narrow their debate even further. דיקלא ואלים, Dikla ve'alim, if
it was a palm tree that got thicker, ארעא ואסקא סירטון, Ara
ve'asik sirton, or it's like a piece of land that now got
enriched, but it's like the thing is seen as the same thing
only bigger, only better, only like in another soil now is richer
or something like that, it got flooded, and now it's wetter. דכולי
עלמא לא פליגי דשקיל. Dekulei alma lo peligi deshakeil. Even the Rabbis
would say that the בכור Bechor gets double there because that's like
the same thing. It's now just a little bit bigger, it's a
little bit, you know, better. It's not like it's a different thing.
That everybody agrees is like the thing the father had and therefore
the בכור Bechor gets double. Like a house that I now added
a room? No, adding a room is different. No, no, no. Adding
a room is different. Adding a room has to come through your
investment. It has to happen automatically. But he's saying even automatic where
the Rabbis say no, there are cases where the Rabbis will say
yes by automatic.
Anyway, כי פליגי דכפורא והוי שבלי. Ki pligi dekfura vehawei shubli.
When do they disagree? If something was basically like שחת, Shachas, what
is it? It's like fodder. It's like you know, it's like the
grain that's just starting to, the shoots that are just starting to
come out of the ground. And now it became stalks. So you
don't say, I mean physically it's the same thing, but you don't,
it doesn't have the same name. It wasn't you know, stalks that
ripen, stalks that ripened. It was shoots that are now stalks. Okay,
or שלופפי והוי תמרי Shlufifi vehawei tamri
or like little saplings that now are date palms. Okay, so obviously
it's totally natural growth, but it's considered a different object. דמר סבר
שבחא דממילא, Demar savar shivcha dirmimeila, one says it's the same thing,
it's just grown naturally. ומר סבר אשתני, Umar savar ishtani, no, it's
a different object. Okay, so here we're actually saying that the רבנן
Rabbanan would agree in minor cases like it's what Michael said. One
minute. So you're telling me that we all owned this cow, okay,
and and Dad died a month ago, and now we have to
figure out how much did each cow increase in its weight since
the last month and we have to not give a double portion
in that? You know, I mean it gets a little crazy, right?
So no, if it's basically the same thing and it's some just
natural growth of getting a little bigger, we consider that like that
was already in the possession of the father. Okay, but if it's
something brand new, like maybe a debt coming in, or you know,
whatever, or it's a different name of something, it really transforms. It's
called something else, that's right. Correct. Or it's like money that we're
getting from a rental property, right, which is obviously new cash that's
coming in, that's where we're debating. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי חייא, Amar
Rabba bar Bar Chana amar Rabbi Chiyya, עשה כדברי רבי עשה, כדברי
חכמים עשה. Asa kidivrei Rabbi asa, kidivrei chachamim asa. It's like, it's
you know what, there's no clear פסק Psak in this case about
רבי Rabbi or the חכמים. Chachamim. So if a judge wants to
rule one way it's legitimate, he wants to rule the other way
it's legitimate. There's no accepted פסק. Psak. If there's an accepted פסק
Psak and you ruled one way, the wrong way, then we would
say you know you have to, that's like called טועה בדבר משנה,
Toeh bidvar mishna, right? You know, or what happens if something you
know, once something is, that's all these fascinating questions about like what
makes something פסק הלכה. Psak halacha. All these all these are all
discussions about what's considered טועה בדבר משנה, Toeh bidvar mishna, what stage
is something considered to be like bottom line הלכה Halacha that you
can no longer take a different opinion about. But here it says
they're both considered legitimate and a דיין Dayan is free to decide
which way he wants to go. I assume that a דיין Dayan
has to be consistent. Like here, when this person comes before me
and I like this בכור, Bechor, I'll rule like רבי. Rabbi. When
the other person comes before me and I don't like this בכור,
Bechor, I'll rule like the חכמים. Chachamim. I don't think I'm allowed
to do that. But also, you know, you can imagine venue shopping,
right? Here comes the brothers and they have to decide which בית
דין Beis din they're going to go to. You want to find
out well, you know, it's sort of like the Supreme Court confirmation,
like you know if you're very smart you don't publish anything in
your early career so they can't hold you accountable for any position,
right? But like people are going to want to choose you know,
when we have just privately, it's like oh I've got a כשרות
שאלה, Kashrus sheilah, I've got an עירוב שאלה, Eruv sheilah, I know
exactly which רבי Rabbi to call, right? So anyway, it's very interesting
here like which בית דין Beis din are you going to go
to. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, let me just read מסתפקא
ליה, Mistafeik lei, he doesn't know אי הלכה כרבי מחבירו ולא מחביריו.
Ei halacha keRabbi mechaveiro velo mechaveirav. When we normally say we rule
like רבי Rabbi when he against his colleague. So the question is,
is it we go with רבי Rabbi when he argues with one
colleague or against his colleagues even if he argues with many? So
he didn't know which is our general principle of פסק. Psak. It's
not just a question how do we rule in this case, it's
a question of a general principle of פסק. Psak. Do we say
הלכה כרבי מחבירו ולא מחביריו, Halacha keRabbi mechaveiro velo mechaveirav, we go
with רבי Rabbi against a colleague but not
colleagues? או הלכה כרבי מחבירו ואפילו מחביריו, O halacha keRabbi mechaveiro veafilu
mechaveirav, we rule like רבי Rabbi against his against one colleague and
even against multiple colleagues. Even if he's a minority opinion? Even if
he's a minority opinion. So therefore unless again doesn't mean a hundred
percent of the time, but unless we know otherwise. So therefore he
doesn't know, it's רבי Rabbi against the חכמים. Chachamim. Would the rule
say you rule like רבי Rabbi or does the rule say go
like חכמים? Chachamim? He didn't know so either פסק Psak is a
viable פסק. Psak. Yes Gloria. I was thinking that maybe there's a
way to read to narrow that difference in terms of you first
have a פסק psak question to decide is this thing itself a
natural developing,
right. Right.
So that if you viewed this question as being the judge is
free to decide the fact piece, that limits it's not the law.
Yeah, I don't see the גמרא Gemara saying that, especially because here
it says the question is הלכה כרבי מחברו מחבריו, halacha k'Rebbi me'chavero
me'chaverav, but what you do point out, and that was similar you
know Mike asked before, how do you determine what's natural, you know,
what meant because so you know I had a friend, he's a
legal scholar now, חיים Chaim Saiman, he like he writes sometimes about
הלכה halacha and secular legal theory or whatever. And he said, you
know, the גמרא Gemara work were like all of its efforts are
about determining what the law is. And there's like almost no effort
in determining how you assess the facts. And he says in any
normal like, you know, legal system, at least as much effort is
going into the question of determining whether the facts satisfy the requirements
as opposed to just what the requirements are. So his point was
that that shows it was much more of a theoretical system than
a practical system, because you know, because it didn't have to put
in that effort that gets fought out in the actual courts about
how you exactly assess the facts. Yes. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: we're not done. That was one opinion, that
like either position is legitimate.
אמר רב נחמן אמר רב, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rav, so רב
נחמן Rav Nachman says in רב, Rav, אסור לעשות כדברי רבי. assur
la'asot k'divrei Rebbi. No. And meaning, and the רשב"ם Rashbam says we're
not just saying הלכה כחכמים. halacha k'chachamim. Since before we were saying
it's okay to פוסק pasken each way, he's saying no, we're not
allowed to פוסק pasken like רבי. Rebbi. His position is rejected and
if you did we might have to revert your judgment.
קסבר הלכה כרבי מחברו ולא מחבריו. Kasavar halacha k'Rebbi me'chavero v'lo me'chaverav.
We rule like him against one friend but not against many. רב
נחמן דידיה אמר, Rav Nachman didei amar, רב נחמן Rav Nachman in
his own name says, because that was רב נחמן Rav Nachman in
the name of רב, Rav, מותר לעשות כדברי רבי. mutar la'asot k'divrei
Rebbi. You're allowed to rule like רבי, Rebbi, which is a little
different than either way is fine. You're allowed to rule like רבי
Rebbi sounds like there's a maybe there's a preference to go like
the חכמים, Chachamim, but if רבי, Rebbi, you find רבי Rebbi persuasive
you're allowed to rule like him.
קסבר Kasavar but the גמרא Gemara interprets it. The גמרא Gemara interprets
מותר לעשות כדברי רבי mutar la'asot k'divrei Rebbi as חייב לעשות כדברי
רבי. chayav la'asot k'divrei Rebbi. קסבר הלכה כרבי מחברו ואפילו מחבריו. Kasavar
halacha k'Rebbi me'chavero v'afillu me'chaverav. I don't understand how the גמרא Gemara
makes that jump. Okay. Yes. So you only are saying it can
be like רבי Rebbi even against the חכמים, Chachamim, like you have
a choice. And when you say הלכה, halacha, you know, I don't
know, אפילו afillu you mean to read אפילו מחבריו afillu me'chaverav
meaning it's you're allowed to rule against him מחבריו? me'chaverav? It's interesting.
I don't think that's normally how it is, but it's interesting.
I mean that would certainly fit how it's connecting the two here
with the line מותר. mutar. Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now רבא's
Rava saying something that's more clear about a question about like a
preferred פסק. psak. אסור לעשות כדברי רבי, assur la'asot k'divrei Rebbi, but
it's said a little harsher: you're not allowed to, but אם עשה
עשוי. im asa asuy. If you ruled that way, we're not going
to reverse the judgment. So it's really, it is not the acceptable
פסק, psak, but it is a legitimate enough that we are not
going to reverse a judgment. Okay. קסבר מטין אתמר. Kasavar matin itmar.
We're inclined to go like the חכמים, Chachamim, we default to the
חכמים's Chachamim position, but we don't completely reject רבי's Rebbi position. Okay.
So that was interesting in general about like what are the rules
about רבי Rebbi when he argues with his colleagues and a range
of possibilities there. תני רב נחמן בשאר ספרי דבי רב. Tani Rav
Nachman bish'ar sifrei d'vei Rav. Now רב נחמן Rav Nachman taught in
the other books of the house of רב. Rav. What does this
mean the other books of the house of רב? Rav? So I
want to read you a רשב"ם Rashbam which is very important. What
are the names of the מדרשי הלכה? Midreshei Halacha? Anybody know? What's
the name of the מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha on
שמות? Shemos? מכילתא. Mechilta. What's the name of the מדרש הלכה Midrash
Halacha on ויקרא? Vayikra? ספרא. Sifra. What's the name of the מדרש
הלכה Midrash Halacha on במדבר Bamidbar and דברים? Devarim? ספרי. Sifrei. What
do these words mean? Book, the book or whatever, books, ספרא Sifra
means the book, fine, the book, books, and מכילתא Mechilta means collection.
Collection. Very descriptive names. Okay, so שאר ספרי דבי רב, sh'ar sifrei
d'vei Rav, the ספרא, Sifra, the book is the מדרש הלכה Midrash
Halacha on ויקרא, Vayikra, and because that is the earliest מדרש הלכה,
Midrash Halacha, there's actually a wonderful article by שלמה נאה, Shlomo Naeh,
he claims that he thinks that it was the actual first תורה
שבעל פה Torah Sheba'al Peh that was ever written down, was the
מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha on ויקרא. Vayikra. It's clearly the most developed
and the largest, okay, that's the ספרא. Sifra. The ספרי, Sifrei, oh
on you know, the other books, right, are the ones that are
on במדבר Bamidbar and דברים, Devarim, and this is really the ספרי
Sifrei is שאר ספרי דבי רב. sh'ar sifrei d'vei Rav. The remaining,
the other books of the house of רב. Rav. Why they're exactly
called רב, Rav, okay, some ספרא Sifra is, some actually if you
take some editions of the ספרי, Sifrei, it'll say on it ספרי
דבי רב. Sifrei d'vei Rav. Okay, and the מכילתא, Mechilta, according to
the רשב"ם, Rashbam, that's also included in the שאר ספרי, Shear Sifrei,
the other books. This is the main book and the others are
the other books. Okay? Do you have two מכילתות? Mechiltos? Well, there's
also two of everything. There's the מכילתא דרבי ישמעאל Mechilta de-Rabbi Yishmael
and the מכילתא דרבי שמעון. Mechilta de-Rabbi Shimon. I know, there's two
of everything. There's the רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael has... we don't have
the manuscripts of all. But there's two parallel ספריס Sifre's as well.
There's two... I mean but the מכילתא Mechilta we have the full
like different... both from the רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael school and the
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva school. So take a look at the רשב"ם,
Rashbam, I just love this because it's like a little, you know,
bibliographical and academic. בשאר ספרי דבי רב, Be-Shear Sifrei Debei Rav, it's
like right under the הגהות הב"ח Hagahot Ha-Bach finishes. He says: ספרי
דבי רב היינו תורת כהנים, Sifrei Debei Rav haynu Torat Kohanim, ברייתא
דשל ספר ויקרא. Braita de-shel Sefer Vayikra. שאר ספרי דבי רב קרי
ליה מדרש של ספר במדבר מויהי בנסע המחנה עד סופו דספר, Shear
Sifrei Debei Rav karei lei Midrash shel Sefer Bamidbar mivi-yehi binesoa hamachaneh
ad sofo d'sefer, ואלה הדברים וכולו Ve-eileh ha-devarim ve-chulo that should be
not כולי, kulei, כולו, kulo, ומכילתא דהיינו מדרש אלה שמות מהחודש הזה
לכם עד סופו דספר. u-Mechilta d'haynu Midrash eileh Shemot me-hachodesh hazeh lachem
ad sofo d'sefer.
כולהו איקרי Kulu ikrei all those three are called... כולהו איקרי kulu
ikrei lost my place... שאר ספרי דבי רב. Shear Sifrei Debei Rav.
והיינו דאמרינן בעלמא סתם מתניתין רבי מאיר סתם ספרא רבי יהודה, Ve-haynu
d'amrinan be-alma Stam Matnitin Rabbi Meir Stam Sifra Rabbi Yehuda, all of
these are תלמידי רבי עקיבא. Talmidei Rabbi Akiva. Okay, so the סתם,
stam, the anonymous voice in the משנה Mishna is רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, the anonymous voice in the ספרא Sifra is רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. סתם ספרי, Stam Sifrei, so again that's the ספרי, Sifrei, רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, who is רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai. סתם סדר עולם רבי יוסי סתם תוספתא רבי נחמיה וכולן אליבא
דרבי עקיבא. Stam Seder Olam Rabbi Yose Stam Tosefta Rabbi Nechemia ve-kullan
aliba de-Rabbi Akiva. Okay, and they're all according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva.
I don't know where רב Rav presumably does not mean רב Rav
the אמורא. Amora. I don't know if רב Rav just means like
the you know the rabbis or whatever. I'm not exactly sure, somebody
I'm sure knows, whatever, about what the דבי רב Debei Rav part
means... except, you know, but it might just mean like the ישיבה,
yeshiva, you know, I don't know if they say there in the
English they have a footnote or whatever. You can tell me if
it says something about the word רב. Rav. What's the וכולן אליבא
דרבי עקיבא ve-kullan aliba de-Rabbi Akiva mean? They're all of them are
following the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position because those are all תלמידי
רבי עקיבא. Talmidei Rabbi Akiva. You know, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, whatever are all תלמידי רבי עקיבא, Talmidei Rabbi Akiva,
meaning it's the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva school. This is what... this
is what Rabbi Dov was saying because we have, we have parallels
of these from רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael school. Now actually, the מכילתות
Mechiltas that we have, the standard מכילתא Mechilta that people have is
מכילתא דרבי ישמעאל, Mechilta de-Rabbi Yishmael, which is not the one of
the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva school. There's a מכילתא דרשב"י, Mechilta de-Rashbi,
notice that... notice who the רשב"ם Rashbam said that the... that the
סתם ספרי Stam Sifrei is according to? רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, which
is רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. Okay? So מכילתא
דרשב"י Mechilta de-Rashbi is רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai
is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. This is the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
school. Okay? So when we say סתם מכילתא Stam Mechilta or whatever,
סתם ספרי, Stam Sifrei, now these ספרי Sifrei are... anyway the ספרא
Sifra is רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, we don't have a ספרא Sifra
from the רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael school, but the beginning of the
ספרא Sifra is... anybody know the first thing in the ספרא? Sifra?
The י"ג מדות Yud Gimmel Middot according to רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
So it's very bizarre we have a piece of it from רבי
ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, okay? But the ספרא Sifra really is here in
the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva school, okay? Except for the י"ג מדות
Yud Gimmel Middot which is in the beginning of
it. And the ספרי... Sifrei... I think the ספרי Sifrei is the
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the one we have that's called ספרי, Sifrei,
and then there's ספרי זוטא Sifrei Zuta which I think is if
I'm getting this right, the רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael school. So they
really were parallels, we don't have everything. The standard books we have
are the ספרא Sifra and the ספרי Sifrei which is רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and the מכילתא Mechilta which is רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
But we have since found pretty full manuscripts of the מכילתא דרשב"י.
Mechilta de-Rashbi. Yes? Just it says what it has is early authorities
disagree with regard to the meaning of the term דבי רב Debei
Rav in this context. The רמב"ם Rambam indicates in the משנה תורה
Mishneh Torah that דבי רב Debei Rav refers to the school of
רב Rav who edited these volumes. Oh so that they were eventually
edited, meaning even though they were done by the תנאים, Tannaim, the
final editing occurred by רב. Rav. Okay? And רש"י Rashi interpreted it
in חולין Hulin to mean the study hall and he explains that
the expression refers to מדרש Midrash that was familiar to everyone in
the study hall. Ah, so like דבי רב Debei Rav means the
ישיבה, yeshiva, right. Okay, good. Very good. The two possibilities I guess
were רש"י Rashi and the רמב"ם. Rambam. Excellent. Okay, yes? Two things
real quick. One is I don't know where, you know, there's also
a work of the ל"ב מדות Lamed Bet Middot of רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. Right. And that might be רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, correct.
Okay, right. So let's go on. The גמרא Gemara says like this:
So, תניא רמי בר חמא בשאר ספרי דבי רב. tanya Rami bar
Chama be-Shear Sifrei Debei Rav. So this is his ברייתא braita he
has from the ספרי Sifrei because this is going to be a
דרש drash on a פסוק pasuk in דברים. Devarim. So it's from
the ספרי, Sifrei, that's why we're mentioning it. Okay? בכל אשר ימצא
לו, Be-chol asher yimatzei lo, right, the בכור bechor gets double with
everything that is found belonging to the father.
פרט לשבח ששבחו נכסים לאחר מיתת אביהם. Perat le-shevach she-shavchu nechasim le-achar
mitat avi-hem. So it has to be everything that the father had
when he died. Excludes an increase in value that occurred after the
father died. וכל שכן שבח שהשביחו יורשין לאחר מיתת אביהם. Ve-chol she-ken
shevach she-hishpichu yorshin le-achar mitat avi-hem. Certainly doesn't get double in an
increase that came because the heirs were the ones that actively increased
the value.
דלא שקיל, De-lo shakil, he doesn't get. ומני רבנן היא. Umani rabanan
hi. And according to that ברייתא, Baraita, that ברייתא Baraita is according
to the רבנן, Rabanan, not רבי. Rebbi. You don't get an actual
increase in value. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel. So now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says in the name of
שמואל, Shmuel, אין בכור נוטל פי שנים במלוה. ein bechor notel pi
shenayim b'milveh. Okay, now we're going to get to the question about
a loan. A בכור bechor does not get double in a loan.
למאן? L'man? Now according to who? אילימא לרבנן, Ileima l'rabanan, if it's
according to the
רבנן, Rabanan, השתא שבחא דאיתא ברשותיה אמרו רבנן לא שקיל. hashta shivcha
d'isa birshusei amru rabanan lo shakil. Something that you actually in your
possession like a cow that gave birth, even though the cow was
in the possession and happened naturally. You're going to tell me that
the בכור bechor doesn't get double, that's not considered to be in
the father's estate.
מלוה מיבעיא, milveh mibaya, a loan that the money was completely out
of the control of the estate. Of course that's new money. That's
what the גמרא Gemara is assuming right now, that a loan is
money owed to the estate is considered new money, because when the
father died it was completely out of his control. So certainly the
Rabbis would say you don't get double. אלא לרבי. Ela l'Rebbi. We
must be according to רבי. Rebbi. For רבי, Rebbi, you would, that's
considered like natural increase, but for the רבנן Rabanan you would not
get double. That's our first position. A loan is considered to be
increase and not part of the estate, not
naturally part of the estate for the רבנן. Rabanan. But one minute.
והא דתניא, Veha detanya, that which we taught in the ברייתא. Baraita.
ירשו שטר חוב, Yarshu shetar chov, if they inherit a document of
debt, they inherit a debt, a money owed to them with a
document.
ירשו שטר חוב, Yarshu shetar chov, בכור נוטל פי שנים, bechor notel
pi shenayim, the בכור bechor gets double, בין במלוה בין בריבית, bein
b'milveh bein b'ribis, whether it's a מלוה milveh or even in ריבית.
ribis. Now what do you mean ריבית? ribis? You're not supposed to
collect ריבית. ribis. Any guesses?
When would we be able to say ריבית ribis without pausing about
the legalities of it? Non-Jew. Exactly. Okay, so money owed by a
non-Jew whether it's the principal or the ריבית, ribis, the בכור bechor
gets double. So the only person that could be, right, is רבי,
Rebbi, right, as you said before. So now the גמרא Gemara says
מני? Mani? So who is that? You just got through saying that
the line says that a בכור, bechor, I'm sorry I might have
misstated this, the line said a בכור bechor doesn't get double in
a debt. So what we said is, I might have misstated this.
What we said is that's obvious according to the רבנן, Rabanan, he
doesn't get double in a debt. So the line that he doesn't
get double in a debt must be according to רבי, Rebbi, that
even according to רבי Rebbi that's considered to be totally new money.
So גמרא Gemara says it can't be, because we have a ברייתא
Baraita that says a בכור bechor gets double in a debt and
even in the interest. So clearly at least רבי Rebbi says that
a בכור bechor gets double in a debt. So the גמרא Gemara
says מני? Mani? So לא רבי ולא רבנן? lo Rebbi velo Rabanan?
If you said רבי Rebbi says he doesn't, this ברייתא Baraita that
says a בכור bechor gets double, who's it going like? So the
גמרא Gemara says fine. You're right. According to רבי Rebbi a בכור
bechor gets double in a debt, double in the interest, that's natural
increase. That's according to רבי. Rebbi. The ברייתא Baraita that says a
בכור bechor doesn't get double in a debt, לעולם רבנן. l'olam Rabanan.
Now you said it was obvious? It's not obvious. צריכא. tzerich. You
need to tell me that for the רבנן Rabanan a debt is,
even a debt is considered new money. Why? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salika
da'atach amina, I would have thought like we all thought when we
discussed this earlier, מלוה כיון דנקיט שטרא כמאן דגביא דמיא, milveh keivan
d'nakit shetara k'man d'gavya damya,
right? If you have money owed and you actually have the document
and you could also say and you have liens on people's property,
you're holding a physical document which represents the debt, you have concrete
liens on somebody's property, it's money owed you, it's a reasonable thing
to say that according to the רבנן Rabanan that's considered to be
part of the estate. Right, that is very reasonable.
So קא משמע לן kamashmalan that it's not. So what we're saying
now is, I mean for us, I think like we discussed earlier,
a lot of us think, hey, that actually should be part of
the estate. But the גמרא Gemara says no, it divides along the
רבי Rebbi and the רבנן Rabanan line. For the רבנן, Rabanan, even
with a שטר shetar and even with liens, money owed to the
estate is not part of the estate and the בכור bechor does
not get double. And for רבי Rebbi it is, and not only
is the principal part of the estate, even the interest, because how's
it any different than you know money from a rental property, right?
Even the interest, it happens automatically and therefore for רבי Rebbi it's
all part of the estate. Okay, so let's see if we can
read one more line. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
Where were we? שלחו מתם, Shalachu mitam, they sent from ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. בכור נוטל פי שנים במלוה אבל לא בריבית. bechor notel
pi shenayim b'milveh aval lo b'ribis. So now we're going to split,
the principal yes, not the ריבית. ribis. So למאן? l'man? Who is
this going like? אילימא לרבנן, Ileima l'rabanan, we just got through saying
for the Rabbis, השתא שבחא דאיתא ברשותיה אמרו רבנן דלא שקיל, hashta
shivcha d'isa birshusei amru rabanan d'lo shakil, if the Rabbis say you
don't get the increase that's natural like the cow, מלוה מיבעיא? milveh
mibaya? So they wouldn't say you get the מלוה, milveh, anyway we
just said that the Rabbis said you didn't get a loan, the
בכור bechor didn't get double of a loan. אלא לרבי? Ela l'Rebbi?
But לרבי וריבית סבר l'Rebbi v'ribis sabar wait one minute you said
רבי Rebbi says you do get double even. and in the interest.
So we have one ברייתא Braisa says you get double in the
interest. That has to be רבי. Rabbi. We have one ברייתא Braisa
says that a בכור—we Bechor have one statement that says a בכור
Bechor doesn't get double even in the principal of the loan. We
said that's the
רבנן. Rabbanan. Now we have a middle position that says he gets
double in the principal but not the interest. So who's that go
like? So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם רבנן היא Le'olam Rabbanan hi
ומלוה כמאן דגביא דמי. u'milva k'man d'gabya dami. No, there's a debate
what the רבנן Rabbanan hold. Okay, so thankfully even this what we
said, it should be like it's part of the estate even according
to the רבנן, Rabbanan, that actually is a—is an opinion. Okay, so
רבי Rabbi says he gets—he gets that both the principal, principal and
the interest is part of the estate, okay, and for the רבנן
Rabbanan we have two versions. We have the שלחו מתם Shalchu mi'tam
version which says the principal is part of the estate because it
actually—you have a שטר, Shtar, you have liens, it's like you're holding
on to it, it's owed to the estate, it is. The ריבית
Ribbis is not. And then we have the first version which was—who
was the first
version? רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel,
אמר שמואל amar Shmuel that says
nothing. No—is part of the estate. You know, neither the principal nor
the interest. A שטר Shtar is not enough to make it... Correct.
So רבי Rabbi says, which makes sense, if he says money from
an—from a, you know, from an—I—you know, a rental property is considered
part of the estate, it happens automatically, so he says the same
about the loan, principal and the interest. The question is for the
רבנן, Rabbanan, is the principal of a loan that—of—of a debt owed
to the estate with a שטר Shtar and with liens, is that
enough to be considered part of the estate? One version says yes
and one version says no. But not on the principal, on the
interest. No, of course the interest is not for the רבנן. Rabbanan.
The question is would at least the principal be considered enough? Yeah,
okay. All right, so we'll wrap up.